Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to
be learning about gas law stoichiometry.
In this two part video, in part one we
are going to be going over STP related
gas law stoichiometry equations, meaning
that STP is what we refer to as a
standardized temperature and pressure.
If you are interested in part two, that's
going to be looking more specifically
at how to use the ideal gas law.
Referring to when we have a chemical
equation for both of them, when it's
balanced, which scenario can you apply?
So to make this video a little bit
shorter, I split it into two parts.
So if you're interested in one versus
the other, Please go check them both out.
All right, so we're first going to start
with the STP version of this video.
First thing is we're going to be
looking at the two different types of
problems that you'll see with gas laws.
As you may remember from gas laws is that
there are dozens of formulas it feels
like, but the good news is you really
only need to know about two different
types, which is looking at the word
problem and dissecting it correctly, which
we're going to go through the tips and
tricks of how to decipher these things.
Especially if you're struggling
in general chemistry.
So look at the different problems and
you can sort, go by chapter by chapter to
really down below when you scroll to help
you go to the problem you need help with.
Now with this STP, just as a reminder,
that's when you have the standard
temperature and pressure, meaning that all
the conditions are defined for you, right?
Temperature is 273 Kelvin, pressure is
one atmosphere, and we also have access
to the molar volume, which means that 22.
4 liters of any gas.
is equivalent to one mole of a gas.
Now if it's not at STP, or even if it is,
you still could use the ideal gas law.
Um, but when it comes to the ideal
gas law, this is always referring to
what the current condition is of the
gas after the reaction occurred, or
even before the reaction occurred.
So what is the condition?
Now the big thing about this is you
have four different variables, which are
pressure, volume, temperature, and moles.
You need three out of four of these
to be able to use this formula, or
it can get a little bit tricky and a
little complicated, so generally you're
always given three out of the four.
So when we are looking at these, we
are going to be exploring all the
different formulas in many different
problems, so let's take a look at
how to use these starting with STP.
Now when it comes to stoichiometry,
the whole idea is that this is
all about unit cancellation.
So same thing as dimensional
analysis and all the, most of the
conversions you do in chemistry.
Now, the thing with stoichiometry
is that generally it uses a
balanced chemical equation.
But what we're going to start with
is some problems that don't involve
a chemical equation, just to get
some of the basics to remind us.
of unit cancellation.
So the first problem here is
how many moles of neon are
in six liters of gas at STP?
Well, with this problem, you are still
doing unit cancellation, but you're
involving moles, which is still talking
about how we can read these problems.
So the first thing is, if we notice
is that it starts with a given number,
always write down your numeric values,
nine times out of 10, they are important.
So we have six liters.
Now, being that this is an STP,
what we can use is, is that
molar volume, which was 22.
4 liters, is equivalent to one mole.
So being that we can use that,
we want to cancel our units.
So being that we have liters
on top, that means we need
liters also on the bottom here.
So 22.
4 liters.
We now see that, oh, our units are
going to cancel, which is fantastic,
and that's equivalent to one mole.
So what does this mean as a little
t table, if this is your first time
seeing these, is you do 6 divided by 22.
4, and you will get your number here.
So what we are going to get is 0.
268 moles, but being that we started
with two significant figures, so you
can see that up here, there's two
digits, We are going to round this to 0.
27 moles.
All right, let's take
a look at the next one.
So what if I want to do the other way?
So how many liters would 2.
4 moles of argon occupy at STP?
Well, same idea, right?
If I have 2.
4 moles, that's going to be on top.
We will put one mole on the bottom, 22.
4 liters on top.
And what we can once again see
is, hey, mole, mole, cancel.
So we now have 2.
4 times 22.
4 And as a result, what
we are going to get is 53.
76 liters, and we are going to once
again round that to two sig figs,
so we are going to get 54 liters.
And when we're done, we want to box our
answer off, just like I should have did
earlier, and that is how you do it with
just how to use the STP conversion.
Let's take a look at
some chemical equations.
Now when we work with STP, it
is really important that you
realize when it is an STP.
Generally it's always listed
in the problem that we have it.
So even though I have the title above,
so you can see it in the problem
too, so it says calculate the volume.
in liters of ammonia produced when 5.
5 liters of H2 react
with excess N2 at STP.
Okay, so we have this thing that says STP.
That's really important.
That means your problem
is 10 times easier.
You do not have to use the ideal gas law.
There's some other key piece
of information too, right?
We were given Uh, the number, we have
the number of liters of hydrogen and
it tells us we have excess nitrogen,
meaning that doesn't run out.
So it only has to rely on hydrogen.
This is not a limiting reactant
problem, which is great, right?
You'd have to have both
values to have that.
Now the one thing is if you kind of
notice there's not a chemical equation,
so what you have to do is, is predict
and balance it, which tends to be a
really common theme in a lot of these.
Okay.
Thanks.
So one thing it says is how much ammonia
is produced in the problem, right?
So kind of highlight that
in purple right there.
So when it says it's produced or made or
created, synthesized, oxidized, all these
different terms referring to a reaction,
generally that's probably the product.
So you gotta read it carefully.
Sometimes it depends on
how everything's worded.
But if it says it's made,
that's a sign that, hey, this
has to be on the product side.
All right, so now it also says that
hydrogen and ammonia reacted, right?
So we were given that volume, that excess.
So let's put those over
here just so we have that.
So H2 plus N2.
All right, now how do we balance this?
Well, generally when it comes to
balancing this problem, is you
notice that we have a odd number of
hydrogens here on the right hand side.
When you have an odd subscript, this
is something I like to try, always want
to try first, is even the odds, right?
So what does that mean?
Well, we don't like odd
numbers, so let's make it even.
So let's add a supers, or
coefficient in front of that, of 2.
Now what does that do?
That makes a total of 6
hydrogens on the right.
So what we are now going to do is put a
3 in front of the hydrogens on the left.
Meaning we have six hydrogens
on the left and on the right.
And one thing you might have
noticed is along with that is
how many nitrogens you now have.
Well, you have two nitrogens now on the
left and you already had two on the right.
So it is balanced and it is happy.
This is exactly what we want.
All right.
So now that we have that, what we're going
to do now is use the piece of information
that was given to us in the problem.
Which as you saw, we had 5.
5 liters of hydrogen.
And that is at STP.
So let's kind of write that down.
So what we are, what we also are
trying to figure out as well is
how much ammonia was produced.
We have to use our chemical reaction.
So the first thing what
we have was that 5.
5 liters, right, of H2.
And this is where it's really
important that you're kind of
writing out all your different units.
all your species so that way you're
not getting them like mixed up
when you're showing them because
the molecules have to cancel too.
So one thing about this is that
you see, okay, if you remember
our relationship we had 22.
4 liters is equivalent to
one mole of hydrogen, right?
So we'll write hydrogen for both
these and we see that liters of
hydrogen cancels liters of hydrogen.
Now that we have moles, right,
your goal is always the mole.
If you can get there, you're
half of the way there.
So, which is fantastic.
And we want to get to ammonia.
So, what we now need to do is read
our chemical equation, which you
can see three moles of hydrogen is
equivalent to two moles of ammonia.
So what we are going to do is
we're going to write our three
moles of hydrogen on the bottom.
Reason is, is because now you can
see that, hey, your units now cancel.
And now we're going to put two moles
of of ammonia on, or on top, okay?
And then we're going to finish
it with that, um, that molar
volume once again, right?
So we're one mole of NH3.
Remember any gas is equivalent to 22.
4 liters of NH3.
And the last thing is you can
see once again units cancel
here as well, which is awesome.
Now the thing about this problem is that
you might notice something if you are
math savvy is that there is more to this
than I can't stop other than the units.
One thing you'll see is that the 22.
4 liters down here are on
top here cancels the 22.
4 liters all the way on
the other side, right?
There's many different
things that can cancel.
Same thing with one mole and
one mole all the way across.
So wait a minute, can this
problem be a lot easier?
And the answer is absolutely it can.
So everything's cleaned up.
Now what we can actually do
is when the problem is at STP,
you can use the coefficients to
define a liter to liter ratio.
So meaning that going off our chemical
formula is that two liters of ammonia is
equivalent to three liters of hydrogen.
And that's because of
kinetic molecular theory.
All the gases are indiscriminate
particles that you can't tell
the difference between, so there
is a relationship between them.
So you'll get the exact same answer.
So all we have to do is do five and
a half, divide by three, multiply
by two, and what we will get is 3.
7 liters of ammonia.
So you can kind of, you can ignore all
that craziness of that long problem.
So this is when it is at STP that you
can do this step for a volume to volume.
It's nice to know the little tricks
because it can save you a lot of time on
exams that you're limited on your time.
Let's look at another.
Stoichiometry at STP.
So if you have a chemical equation,
you generally will have to do
some stoichiometry, meaning that
we're going to have to use the
mole to mole volume very often.
So, with this problem, the metabolic
oxidation of glucose, C6H12O6, in our
bodies produces CO2, which is expelled
through our lungs as a gas, right?
You breathe out.
So, if I have, let's say, the following
chemical formula, which is C6H12O6.
glucose, which is combining with
oxygen to make CO2 and water.
Calculate the volume of oxygen required
to oxidize 50 grams of glucose at STP.
Wow, that was a lot of information
in one thing, but it all really
boils down to just knowing the
chemical equation and this last line.
So what do we need, right?
We want the volume and we
started with 50 grams of glucose,
and that's at STP, which is.
Very, very crucial.
So, how do we start?
Well, remember, the goal
is always the mole, right?
How can you get something here to moles?
Well, you gotta kind of think,
going through your chemist's
toolbox, what can you convert?
You have pretty much available
to you are three options.
You have molar mass, the ideal gas law,
or you can essentially use molarity.
Well, there's no molarity here
and you don't have all of the
variables for the ideal gas law.
You have temperature, pressure,
remember you need three out of four.
You don't have everything, but
you do have the essentially
glucose here, which is its mass.
You can always look up the molar
mass via your periodic table.
So if we are to do that, let's say
if we are to get the molar mass for
glucose, so meaning you're going to
take six carbons, uh, multiply it by 12.
011, then you're going to add
that plus 12 hydrogens, each 1.
008, and then add that by the
six oxygens, you will get 180.
156 grams of glucose is equivalent
to one mole, okay, of glucose.
Now, from that, what
can you do from there?
Well, Being that we are curious about
how much, what, calculate the volume
of oxygen here, we can now do the mole
to mole ratio from the problem, right?
This is where the
stoichiometry comes from.
You can see that for every six moles
of O2, there is one mole of C6H12O6,
or glucose, to the equivalent.
So it's one mole, and we'll put C6H12O6
for every six moles of O2, right?
They're equivalent to one another.
So now when that happens you can see
grams cancels grams, our moles of
glucose cancels our moles of glucose,
And we're left with only our moles of O2.
So we want to check that off.
Our unit's all cancelled.
We're good, right?
So if we were to plug this into
our calculator, we'll do 50 times
6, and then divide that by 180.
156.
That will give us how many moles we have.
Now, is that everything?
Are we done?
Well, the thing is, it wants volume.
So what can I do now?
Well, if you remember, STP, right?
So we can do one more step.
We can use our STP, our molar
volume, to do the last step.
We got to our goal, but we want to go
one more step, so one mole of O2 is
now, is going to be equivalent to 22.
4 liters of gas.
Alright, now, if you put now
that into your calculator, what
you are going to get is 37.
3 liters of oxygen gas
is going to be produced.
when you oxidize the 50
grams worth of sugar.
Thank you so much for listening
to part one of this video.
So in this video, as you saw, we
went through the STP versions of how
to look at gas loss stoichiometry.
In part two, we will look at
how to apply the ideal gas law.
So please check out part two following up.
You should be seeing that recommendation
right, right over my face in a second.
So thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped
you please stop by again.
If you have any questions,
please message me, reach out to
me, comment below on the video.
If this is your first time here, please
like and subscribe to the channel.
Please keep helping it grow and help
me help more students just like you.
All right.
Thank you all.
And I hope you have a wonderful day.